Plant, Richard; Papers ger074
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Richard Plant Papers
1950-1981
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger074
1.04 cubic ft.
The collection contains manuscripts, typescripts, book reviews, film reviews, and materials for two unwritten novels all by Richard Plant, professor of German and comparative literature.
Collection X
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Richard Plant between 1979 and 1981.
Historical Note
Richard Plant (1910-1998) was born Richard Plaut in Frankfort, Germany. He was a gay and Jewish author and educator who emigrated first to Switzerland in 1933 and then to the United States of America in 1938. Plant was encouraged to flee Nazi persecution by his father, who was a Jewish Socialist. In 1935, he was awarded a Ph.D. in languages from the University of Basel in Switzerland.
It was during his time in Basel that he wrote the children's book Die Kiste mit dem großen S (1936) as well as several film reviews for Basel's National-Zeitung and even wrote articles under the pseudonym "Richard Plant" in Nazi, Germany. Plant's dissertation the sexual and psychological aspects of the narrative style of Austrian Jewish physician and author Arthur Schnitzler. His next book "Taschenbuch des Films" (1938) was a nonfiction study and analysis of international films.
After graduation, Plant emigrated to New York City and formally Americanized his name to "Richard Rene Plant" and began communicating with other emigres via the left-wing German Jewish weekly Aufbau. After America entered World War II, Plant found employment for three years as a propaganda scriptwriter, translator, and broadcaster for the U.S. Office of War Information and for NBC. He became a naturalized citizen on January 29, 1945. In 1947 he was hired by the City College of the City University of New York. One year later he published his highly autobiographical novel The Dragon in the Forest (1948). Plant would also review books, primarily current German literature and was granted tenure in 1957 and promotion to full professor in 1970.
Notably, Plant wrote the scenario for the opera Lizzie Borden which premiered in 1965. Following his retirement in 1973, he began to devote more of his time to gay activism and began writing a history of the persecution of gay men under Nazi regime. The forward and conclusion are both autobiographical, and his research included traveling to Arolsen, German to review the records of the concentration camp archives. His magnum opus was The Pink Triangle: The Nazi War Against Homosexuals, published in 1986. Plant died in New York City in 1998.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains manuscripts by Richard Plant on short stories involving Germany during Nazi occupation, including the literary sphere and the history of the persecution of gay men under Nazi regime. There are also manuscripts and offprints of articles, book reviews, and film reviews, and materials for two unwritten novels, one about a German émigré family in New York City.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order.
Literature; Germany -- History -- 1933-1945; Germany -- Politics and government.; Jews -- Germany.; Short stories
- "Arthur Schnitzler als Erzähler" Dissertation written by Richard Plant, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Articles not written by Richard Plant in German, 1948; 1954; 1965; 1974; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles written by Richard Plant in English, 1963; 1975; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Biographical sketches for Richard Plant, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Certificate of Appreciation for Plant from Kiwanis Club, 1969 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Christmas and Holiday Cards, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Gessler and Tell: Psychological Patterns in Schiller's Wilhelm Tell" by Richard Plant, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter from Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America, Inc., 1969 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter to Editor of The New Yorker by Richard Plant, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Materials for College "Day of Judgement" short story including Knickerbocker documents, 1949-1951; 1956-1958; 1962-1963; 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Materials for novels on Emigres in USA, 1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Middlebrook dinner" story with notes, 1971 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Notes on Arthur Schnitzler's Literary Technique" by Richard Plant, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Review for "The Germanic Review" by Richard Plant, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Senor Freud and Senor Marx" Story Drafts by Richard Plant, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Short Stories Drafts written in German by Richard Plant, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Short Story Drafts, written by Richard Plant, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Stories Drafts written about Nazi Germany by Richard Plant, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Story Drafts and Notes about Gay Experience in Nazi Germany, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Story Notes, 1965; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- The City College Alumni Magazine, 1962 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "The World of Heinrich Böll" by Richard Plant, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "The Dragon in the Forest" Novel by Richard Plant, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Reviews written in German by Richard Plant, 1966-1980 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)